Okay, in the last video I showed you how
to use a while loop. A while loop and a
for loop are both called are both
tongue twisted. They both belong to the
category of precondition loops.
Precondition loops means it checks the
condition before it runs the loop. So
here for example um we've got a for loop
and I've changed the syntax a little
bit. Um it says let counter equal four,
counter less than four, counter++.
So, what this is doing is it says start
at four, count until you get almost up
to four, but if you pass four, stop the
loop, and then continue on. If you've
noticed, this loop will never run
because it will start the counter at
four, and then it'll check if four is
less than four. Four is not less than
four, so it's just going to skip over
this loop and end. Meaning, a for loop
can run zero times or possibly many
times. Um, in this case, it will run
zero times. The same is true for our
while loop. It checks a condition and
then it runs the loop. So we're checking
if my password is not the same as the
real password. Um and then we're going
to alert the loop ran. So in this case,
hello and hello are exactly the same. So
this condition is going to get checked
and it's just going to skip over it.
Meaning a while loop can run zero and
possibly many times. Let's just see this
in practice. So I'm going to click go
live.
And there it is. nothing ran and maybe
you thought maybe the code isn't
working. So just to prove to you that
it's not just the code um we're going to
put a break point on line 14 and we're
going to reload our page and it paused.
So sure enough this for loop started
executing and we said let's initialize
the counter to four. Now let's see if
four is less than four. It's not. So
skip the loop. And then it came to my
password. So we said while hello is not
equal to hello. Well those are equal. So
this condition is no longer true which
means we should skip this one. And sure
enough it skipped it. Um those are what
are called precondition loops. We check
the condition and then we run the loop.
I am going to show you now something
that is called a postcond condition
loop. A postcond condition loop is for
when you want your code to run at least
once. Both of the previous loops I
showed you ran zero times, but they
could have run many times. The loop I'm
about to show you will always run once,
but might possibly run many times. So,
in order for this to work, I'm going to
create a deposit. Um, and I'm going to
set it to I'm going to create a total
deposit
and I'm going to set it to $0. Sorry, I
can't stop. Um,
then I'm going to create a um continue
to deposit
and I'm going to set it equal to no.
Now I'm going to start my loop. So I'm
going to say do.
And then I want to ask the user if they
want to deposit money. So, I'm going to
say let deposit amount equal um and
we'll just assume that they're going to
enter whole numbers. Um parse int and
we'll prompt them, how much would you
like to deposit.
Once they've given us that amount, we're
going to take our total deposit and
we're going to increase it by the
deposit amount. Um, if you wanted to
write this out in longhand, uh, you
could say total deposit equals total
deposit plus deposit amount. I like
shorthand notation, so we're going to do
total deposit plus equals deposit
amount. Then we need to ask them if they
want to deposit again. So, we'll say
continue to deposit equals prompt
would
you like to deposit more?
And then um I'm going to say yes or no.
And then to clean up my input, they
could enter a lowercase Y. And I still
want to count that as an uppercase Y. To
handle that, I'm going to say dot2
uppercase. What this does is it converts
everything that they entered into the
prompt into uppercase.
Once I've done that, I'm going to get
here to the end of this do statement. So
it says do this code. That means run
that code exactly once. But I might want
that code to repeat. And I'm going to
say while um continue to deposit
is equal to yes. So if they enter yes,
then I want to run the loop again. If
they don't, then the loop will end.
And then once it's done, I'm going to
alert the total deposit.
So I'm going to save this code and I'm
going to come over here and we're going
to stop the present debugger. um and
reload our page. Says, "How much would
you like to deposit?" So, you'll notice
neither of the precondition loops ran
because their condition said not to.
This one hasn't even checked the
condition yet. It just said, "How much
would you like to deposit?" So, I'll say
$100. And then I'll hit okay. Then it
says, "Would you like to deposit more?"
If I say yes and hit enter, it says,
"How much would you like to deposit?"
I'll do another $100. Then it says,
"Would you like to deposit more?" I'll
say no. And then it says 200, meaning
that was the total amount that I had
there. To show you this in the debugger,
I'm going to remove the break. I'm going
to actually leave the break point on
line 14. And we're going to reload this
page. So, we get to our precondition for
loop. Um, meaning it checks the
condition before it runs. And the
condition is not true, so it just skips
the for loop. Now, we get to our while
loop, and it checks the condition before
it runs. the condition isn't true, so it
drops through it. We create our total
deposit and we can we create our
continue to deposit variable. Now we say
let the deposit amount equal how much
would you like to deposit. Notice this
loop has already started running. It
hasn't even checked the condition once.
So we'll give it an amount. We'll say
100. And then we'll hit the next button.
And now our deposit is 100. um we
increment our total deposits. And now we
prompt to see if you would like to
deposit more. So we're going to hit
next. I'm going to say no. I'm going to
hit okay. And then our continue to
deposit is a sorry continue to deposit
is capital N. Capital N is not the same
as capital Y. So now it's evaluating if
this loop should run again. If I had
entered Y, the loop would run again.
Because I've entered N, it says, okay,
the loop is over. Now alert. So notice
this loop ran only once. Um but it ran
at least once and then we'll alert our
deposit and um our code works as we
expected. So if we come back over here
um the main difference between a dowh
loop and a while loop is that a while
loop might never run. A dowh loop will
run at least once. And that concludes
the video on dowhile loops. Thanks for
watching.